Finding Aid for Jesse Gonzales papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jesse Gonzales papers 1968-2014 1982-2012
Gonzales, Jesse
7.7GB online
1 oversize folders
1 linear feet
2014079 Aa 2 UAl
The papers of Jesse Gonzales document the Latino and Hispanic communities in Michigan, primarily within the Lansing area, and elsewhere. Materials include photographs, both analog and digital, as well as personal and biographical information about Gonzales and his family, his poetry and selected writings. Additionally, the papers contain printed materials about cultural and art programs and festivals in the state.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Collection donated by Jesse Gonzales (donor no. 10969 ) in August 2013 and April 2014.
The collection is open without restriction. Digital materials are accessible online only at the Bentley Historical Library.
Native of Albion, Mich. Jesse Gonzales is a lifelong resident of the state. He has been photographing since his high school days. He received his B.A. in History with minor in Journalism from Michigan State University and M.A. in Community College Education from the University of Michigan (1979). Gonzales has also been active in historical documentation of Michigan Latino history. Beginning in the 1960s, while attending college, Jesse Gonzales and his wife Joana have amassed and saved a sizable collection of materials, publications, books, magazines, newspapers, photography art and artwork which documented the Chicano collegiate presence in East Lansing, Kalamazoo, and Ann Arbor, Mich.
During the late 1970s, Jesse Gonzales began exhibiting his photography along with other Latino artists in the Lansing, Mich. area. Several of his photographs were published in "500 years of Chicano History in Pictures" (Albuquerque, N.M.: SouthWest Organizing Project, 1991). Gonzales has photographed in Michigan, California, Illinois, Texas, Puerto Rico, the Dominican Republic, Mexico and Spain. Besides his personal photographic endeavors, Gonzales worked with other Michigan Latinos, students and artists, to create one of the first statewide Latino arts organizations: The Raza Arts & Media Collective, founded in 1975.
One of his favorite photographic subjects is the Virgin of Guadalupe (the Virgin Mary), a figure revered by Mexicans and Chicanos throughout the U.S. He also continues search out signage, representations, figurines, symbols and icons that evoke Latinidad and Chicanismo. Gonzales is drawn to Chicano iconography that evokes the life and spirit of Latino neighborhoods, including graffiti, signage murals, and statuary. This resulted in the production of "El Calendario Hispano de Michigan, 1981." The calendar covered Hispanic social, cultural, political, and historical events in Michigan from 1781 to 1980.
As an educator Jesse Gonzales has worked for the Michigan State University, Michigan Department of Education, and Lansing School District.
The collection is organized in to two series: Topical Files and Visual Materials
The Jesse Gonzales papers include original images created by Jesse Gonzales, as well as collected materials on Latino/Chicano life and culture in Michigan.
Subjects:
Cinco de Mayo (Mexican holiday); All Souls' Day.; Gonzales, Jesse.; Hispanic American art--California.; Hispanic American art--Mexico.; Hispanic American art--Michigan.; Hispanic American art--Texas.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan--Lansing.; Hispanic heritage--Michigan--Lansing.; Lansing Community College (Mich.); Lansing (Mich.); Latino studies--Michigan.; Mexican American folk art.; Michigan State University.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Festivals--Michigan.; Music festivals--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Digital images.; Photographs.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series (1 linear foot) includes personal and biographical information about Gonzales and his family, his poetry and select writings, research notes, collected materials created by and about Michigan cultural and art institutions and artists, printed material about cultural and art programs and festivals in the state. Also a finding aid to the Juana and Jesse Gonzales papers at Michigan State University.
  - Art concepts, 2000-2003 (Box 1)
  - Biographical and personal (Box 1)
  - Calendario,1991, 2004-2006 (Box 1)
    (see also Outsize)
  - Historic research, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Juana and Jesse Gonzales Papers at Michigan State University (Box 1)
  - Julian Samora Research Institute
    - Nexo, 2007-2011 (Box 1)
      (scattered issues)
    - Publications,1998, 2008-2011 (Box 1)
  - Labor study, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Lopez, Carlos (Box 1)
  - Michigan Hispanic Media Association, 1988 (Box 1)
  - National Endowment for the Arts, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Poetry and other writings, 1968-1978 (scattered),2003, 2006 and undated (Box 1)
  - Printed material, collected
    - Festival programs, 2001-2013, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - La Voz, September 2013-April 2014 (Box 1)
    - Latin American and Latino Art in the Midwestern United States by Olga U. Herrera, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, collected (Box 1)
    (mostly printed)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series (0.1 linear feet, 7.7 GB online, and 1 oversize folder) includes images taken by Gonzales during Chicano/Latino cultural and art festivals, concerts, art exhibits, dances, religious ceremonies, public political gatherings. The majority of images were taken in galleries and on locations in Lansing, Lansing Community College and Michigan State University campuses, and other locations in greater Lansing, Mich. area. Images of murals and street art include those taken in Texas, California, and Mexico. Photographs include images of Gonzales family. Among outsize visual material one will find posters and flyers advertising art events, as well as outsize calendars, Michigan legislature resolutions, and two mounted color photographs.
  - Photographs
    - Art concepts, photographs,1993 (?), 2007 and undated (Box 1)
    - Cigar mural and storefront art from Dominican Republic, 2009 (Box 1)
    - Concepts, 2005 and undated (Box 1)
    - Gonzales family, reprints 1946-1951 and 2007 (Box 1)
    - Hispanics for Gore, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Latin Dance at Lansing Community College, 2004 (Box 1)
    - Mayor Tony Benavides re-election fundraising event, 2003 (Box 1)
    - Mexican Independence Day celebration, Lansing, Mich., 2002 (Box 1)
    - Mexican Independence Day celebration, Lansing, Mich., 2003 (Box 1)
    - Owner of Matador Food Industry, Grand Rapids, Mich., undated (Box 1)
    - Voices del Norte, February 1978 (Box 1)
      (issue includes 2 photographs by Gonzales)
  - Digital files
    - Artes Unidas de Michigan Conference on Latino Arts in Michigan, Lansing, Mich., 2006, .ZIP file
    - Bibliography of Michigan Latino History, 1781-1980 Calendario, 2004, .DOC and .DOCX files
    - Cesar Chavez,1990, 1993, 1995 (includes Lansing protest on street naming, March from MSU to the Capital, March following Chavez's death, .ZIP file
    - Cesar Chavez Plaza parade, North Lansing, Mich., 2010, .ZIP file
    - Chicano poetry reading at Lopez Panaderia, Lansing, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
      (features Detroit poet Trinidad Sanchez)
    - Cinco de Mayo celebration honoring Latino veterans, Lansing, Mich., 2012, .ZIP file
    - Commission on Spanish Affairs of Michigan honoring Jesse Gonzales, Lansing, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
    - Cristo Rey Church annual festival, Lansing, Mich., 2007, .ZIP file
    - Cristo Rey annual Good Friday, date unknown (between 2004 and 2011), .ZIP file
    - Cristo Rey church celebration, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Cristo Rey church fiesta, Lansing, Mich., 2012, .ZIP file
    - Cristo Rey church outdoor festival for Mexican Independence Day, Lansing, 2003, .ZIP file
    - Day of Dead class taught by Nora Mendoza at Red Cedar School, East Lansing, 2003, .ZIP file
    - Day of the Dead student celebration, East Lansing, Mich., 2011, .ZIP file
    - Dia de la Raza dance at Lansing Community College, 2004, .ZIP file
    - Dia de los Muertos celebration, discussion, March, and dance, 2011, .ZIP file
    - Dia de los Muertos at Michigan State University Museum, 2008, .ZIP file
    - Dia de los Muertos at San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Diego Rivera performing at Creole Gallery in Lansing, Mich., 2006, .ZIP file
    - Exhibit of Mexican Folk Art and Popular Culture items, Saginaw Art Museum, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Family/community party of Ramiro/Margarita Gonzalez, East Lansing, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Farmworkers rally in Lansing/MSU Latino soccer game, 2003, .ZIP file
    - Gonzales family Christmas, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Great Lakes Folk Festival, East Lansing, Mich., .ZIP file
    - Grupo Aldaco performance, Lansing, Mich., 2009, .ZIP file
    - Grupo Fantasia, 2004, .ZIP file
    - Hispanic heritage celebrations in Lansing, Mich., 2002, .ZIP file
    - Iraqi Boot Memorial showing Hispanic war dead, Lansing, Mich., 2004, .ZIP file
    - Jesse Gonzales' private collection of Virgin de Guadalupe statuary, images, etc., 1979, .ZIP file
    - Julio Perazza commemorative photo exhibit, Lansing, Mich., 2002, .ZIP file
    - Julio Perazza commemorative photography show, Battle Creek
    - Mich., 2002, .ZIP file
    - La Estrella de Norte Tortillera, Saginaw, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
    - La Virgen de Guadelupe in Mexico, Texas, California, Michigan, 2004-2005, .ZIP file
    - Lansing, Mich. United Auto Workers 602 celebration, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Latin Dance, Lansing Community College, 2004, .ZIP file
    - Latino Pachanga in support of President Obama, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Latino gathering to support President Obama, Lansing, Mich., 2012, .ZIP file
    - Local activists interviewing Arizona educators at East Side Community Center, Lansing, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
    - Los Angeles and East Los Angeles murals, signage, etc., 2011, .ZIP file
    - Los Musicas de Puerto Rico performance, East Lansing, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Luna Conjunto band, Adrian, Mich., 2006, .ZIP file
    - Marachi Perla de Mexico performance at Great Lakes Folk Festival, Lansing, Mich., 2012, .ZIP file
    - Marliz Gonzales' alternative quinceañera, East Lansing, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
    - Marliz Gonzales' graduation party, 2008, .ZIP file
    - Mexican and Chicano art Lopez Bakery, Lansing, Mich., 2004, .ZIP file
    - Mexican dancers at Lansing Community College, 2005, (.ZIP file
    - Mexican family presentation of child to Church at St. Joseph Catholic Church, Kalamazoo, Mich., 2005, .ZIP file
    - Mexican Independence Day ceremony, Lansing, 2003, .ZIP file
    - Mexican Popular Arts exhibit, Saginaw Museum, 2005, .ZIP file
    - Michigan State University Chicano/Latino students orientation, 2006, .ZIP file
    - Nora Mendoza art exhibits, 2012, .ZIP files
      - Ferndale, Mich.
      - Lansing, Mich.
      - Oakland, Calif. Images, 2012, .ZIP file
      - Paloma Rosales, "Soldaderas" exhibit, 2009, .ZIP file
    - Personal Nativity sets from Mexico, Lansing, Mich., 2007, .ZIP file
    - Photographic Considerations for Creole Art Show, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Rosa Arenas art exhibit, Lansing, Mich., 2013, .ZIP file
    - Salsa Verde musical performance at MSU Latin is America festival, 2013, .ZIP file
    - San Antonio, Tex. Murals and other images, 2013, .ZIP file
    - San Francisco Mission District murals and other images, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Smithsonian Institution/Michigan State University Museum Day Fiesta, East Lansing, Mich., 2008, .ZIP file
    - Tejano/Latino Music Festival, Lansing, Mich.
      - 2012, .ZIP file
        (1 of 2)
      - 2012, .ZIP file
        (2 of 2)
    - Tejano Music Festival Preparations, 2012, .ZIP file
    - Tejano/Conjunto music talk at MSU, 2009, .ZIP file
    - Unveiling of Cezar Chavez stamp ceremony, 2003, .ZIP file
    - Chicano art calendar, 2010 (Folder 1)
    - El Calendario Hispano de Michigan, 1981 (Folder 1)
    - Michigan Legislature resolutions commemorating Chicano History Week, 1982 and Puerto Rican Week, 1980 (Folder 1)
    - No Es Lejos 2001, 2 mounted photographs color (Folder 1)
    - Posters and flyers advertising Latino/Chicano art festivals and exhibits, some autographed by artists, 1989-2014 (scattered dates) (Folder 1)
    - Sign:Keep Cesar Chavez Avenue, Vote NO on Proposal A, undated (Folder 1)
Related Material
Juana & Jesse Gonzales papers, 1960-2006 at Michigan State University. Collection contains 6 boxes of reports, newsletters, reprints, unpublished papers and news clippings collected by Jesse & Juana Gonzales since the late 1960's through 2006. A significant part of the collection dates from the mid-1960's through the mid-1980's and relates to Chicano student activism on campuses, Chicanos and Latinos in the arts, and materials on the history of Chicanos and Latinos in Michigan including agricultural labor and migrant workers.
Finding aid is available online: http://findingaids.lib.msu.edu/spc/index.php?p=collections/controlcard&id=303